<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new and true relation from Ireland, sent in a letter from Sir Robert Traverse, to Lievtenant James Finch in London ; of a great defeat given by the Protestants army under the command of Sir Charles Vavasour, to twenty foure thousand of the rebels, under the command of O Sulivan Beare, and Macharta Reb, besieging Brandon-bridge ; where five hundred of ours with two thousand of the towne routed them, kild two thousand of them, and took O Sulivan Beare prisoner, and a great booty.</title>
            <author>Travers, Robert, Sir.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8758</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12640990</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12640990</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65018</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63081)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65018)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 252:E148, no 14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new and true relation from Ireland, sent in a letter from Sir Robert Traverse, to Lievtenant James Finch in London ; of a great defeat given by the Protestants army under the command of Sir Charles Vavasour, to twenty foure thousand of the rebels, under the command of O Sulivan Beare, and Macharta Reb, besieging Brandon-bridge ; where five hundred of ours with two thousand of the towne routed them, kild two thousand of them, and took O Sulivan Beare prisoner, and a great booty.</title>
                  <author>Travers, Robert, Sir.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. N., for Edward Blackmore ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Rob Travers.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Vavasour, Charles, --  Sir, d. 1644.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65018:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65018:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A New and true Relation FROM IRELAND, Sent in a Letter from Sir <hi>Robert Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe,</hi> to Lievtenant <hi>James Finch</hi> in <hi>London.</hi> Of a great Defeat given by the Proteſtants Army, under the command of Sir <hi>Charles Vavaſour,</hi> to twenty foure thouſand of the Rebels, under the command of <hi>O Sulivan Beare,</hi> and <hi>Macharta Reh,</hi> beſieging <hi>Brandon-bridge:</hi> Where five hundred of ours with two thouſand of the Towne routed them, kild two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of them, and took <hi>O Sulivan Beare,</hi> priſoner: and a great booty.</p>
            <p>London, Printed by <hi>A. N.</hi> for <hi>Edward Blackmore,</hi> dwelling at the Signe of the <hi>Angell</hi> in <hi>Paules</hi> Church-yard, 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:65018:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65018:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know you cannot but much deſire to hear from your Friends eſpecially having left them in this miſerable diſtracted King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, where nothing is frequent but tumults and bloudy maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres; yet in the midſt of theſe it hath pleaſed Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God to bleſſe your Friends with health: your bed fellow is in good health, and your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in law Maſter <hi>Freake,</hi> and your brother Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Arthur Freake,</hi> I know you doe expect ſome news from hence, and God be prayſed, I never had more cauſe, nor better news to certifie you of, which hath conduced to the glory of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, and the comfort of all us poore diſtreſſed Proteſtants, againſt whom that devouring beaſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65018:3"/>of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath advanced all her Force. About the beginning of this moneth <hi>O Sulivan Beare,</hi> came from the Weſterne parts with twelve thouſand men, and came to <hi>Timoleague,</hi> where Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger O Shahons</hi> dwels and pillaged the towne, and kill'd a great many of the Engliſh barbarouſly, raviſhing their Wives and Daughters, taking the prey of all the town, and ſetting fire to the moſt part of the towne, marched away, and came to <hi>Macha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a Reh.</hi> a great Rebell who had 12000 men, joyning their Forces, marched to <hi>Bandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> and there beſieged the towne and us in it, threatning to put us all to the ſword if we did not preſently render the town, but upon refuſall, they ſet the baſe town on fire, hoping by that meanes to fire the towne of <hi>Bandonbridge,</hi> but God be thanked, it took not that effect which they expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, for the wind blowing pretty hard from the Weſt, kept the fire from us, to our no little joy, and their vexation, who were thus diſappointed of their wicked intentions only by the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Almighty God, to whom let all good Chriſtians render perpetuall thanks for his great mercies ſhewed to his diſtreſſed people: theſe Rebels and their Forces continued before the town ſtrictly beſieging us, &amp; daily ſhooting into
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65018:3"/>the Towne, the ſpace of foure dayes, in which time we had diſpatched certaine Meſſengers to my Lord Preſident of <hi>Munſter</hi> to <hi>Corke,</hi> who hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of our diſtreſſe, ſent Sir <hi>Charles Vavaſour,</hi> who came in the night with only 500. men, and ſome other Engliſh Commanders, and two peeces of Ordnance, who made an aſſault upon them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was light (they not expecting any ſuch thing) which being ſo ſuddenly performed, did ſo diſtract and amaze the Rebels that they ſeemed to be men without life, and we hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this Alarme into the Towne, having 2000. men in readineſſe under the command of the Right Honourble the Lords of <hi>Kenelmech</hi> and <hi>Brahull,</hi> both my Lord of <hi>Corkes</hi> ſonnes (as having before had intelligence of the ſtratagem) did iſſue out upon them, and valiantly aſſailed them, who at the comming of the Towne forces, they were abſolutely rowted, and every man began to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for his ſafetie by flight, nor could the threats nor perſwaſions of their Commanders cauſe them to ſtay, but they all run away, and left their chiefe Commander <hi>O Sulivan Beare,</hi> who was there ſhot and taken priſoner, and had not <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charta Reh</hi> fled, he had beene his companion in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65018:4"/>impriſonment, as he was before in Armes, yet for all their haſt there was at this bickering ſlaine and wounded on the Rebels part to the number of 2000. men, wee loſing but twenty men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide ſome priſoners that were preſently conveyed to <hi>Corke</hi> to my Lord Preſident, who preſently cauſed them all to bee hanged, as for <hi>O Sulivan Beare</hi> we have him in ſure cuſtody untill he may be ſafely conveyed to <hi>Dublin.</hi> Thus we daily ſee by experience how mightily God fighteth for us, to whom be praiſe and glory for evermore: After the flight and maſſacre of theſe miſerable people, the whole ſpoyle of their Campe was taken, which was great, &amp; a great part of it was devided amongſt the the Souldiers to incourage them, the reſt is kept for the reliefe of our men, there was taken ſome 60. head of cattell, ſome proviſion of bread &amp; meat, three barrels, of powder 300. Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, 200. Pikes, with certaine Swords and Skeenes, ſeven Colours, and certaine other things, not worth expreſſing, to the great diſheartning of them, and and incouragement of us.</p>
            <p>The Rebels have ſince aſſembled their ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red run-awayes, which our forces hearing did
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65018:4"/>march towards them, but could not cauſe them to ſtay, nor durſt they fight, the feare which the laſt skirmiſh had ſtricken them into being ſtill in them, and the want of Armes and powder (which if they had, they would ſoone be with us) doth cauſe them (when our men come neere them) to ſhift away through woods and other by wayes, ſo that they will not by any meanes ſtand the hazard of a fight: wee want men and money extraordinarily (for had not God bleſſed us with this little pillage to releeve our men, we had beene in a miſerable condition, but we hope, and daily expect ſupplyes of both from <hi>England,</hi> which if a ſpeedy courſe bee not taken, it will much endanger the loſſe of this Kingdome, and the lives of many thouſands of poore diſtreſſed Proteſtants, for there is ſcarce an Iriſh Gentleman, but is turned to the Rebels, for they call themſelves the holy Catholique Campe, and doe expect ſupplies from ſome for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Enemie. And further to certifie you, they have burned your Father <hi>Freakes</hi> houſe at <hi>Roſe</hi> and the Deanes houſe, and have taken all the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage in and about the Towne, and have left a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65018:5"/>Garriſon there: Your friend hopes ſhortly to ſee you here againe with a ſupply of men and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, your wife, children, and friends are all well, and remember you daily in their prayers to God: ſo till I ſee you (and ever) I ſhall remaine,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your aſſured loving friend, ROB. TRAVIRS.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Brandonbridge</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>this</hi> 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                     <hi>of May.</hi> 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
